Guide to the Wilda Hamerman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Wilda Hamerman papers
1968-1985
YCAL MSS 217
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.83
(2 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
Correspondence, writings, printed materials, clippings, photographs, and other papers related to Wilda Hamerman's work as secretary to Norman Holmes Pearson. Correspondents consist of Bryher, Pearson, and others, including several Japanese students. Bryher correspondence concerns the completion of the manuscript of The Days of Mars, which Wilda Hamerman typed. The bulk of the letters and postcards from Pearson date from a 1970 trip he took to Australia and many parts of Asia. Writings of others include typescripts and printed essays by Pearson, including a journal of his 1970 trip; an uncorrected proof of Ladislas Farago's Game of the Foxes; and an outline and excerpts from How I Enjoyed Studying in America by Tamotsu Nishiyama. Other papers include clippings of obituaries and printed materials related to Pearson. Photographs all feature Pearson, in individual or group portraits.
Hamerman, Wilda
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Wilda Hamerman, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Broadside folder: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
WILDA HAMERMAN
During the late 1960s and early 1970s, Wilda Hamerman worked as secretary to Norman Holmes Pearson, a professor of English and American Studies at Yale. Pearson was also faculty advisor to the Yale Collection of American Literature and literary executor of both H. D. and Bryher. Wilda Hamerman is married to Martin Hamerman.
Scope and Contents
The Wilda Hamerman Papers consist of correspondence, writings, clippings, photographs and other papers related to Wilda Hamerman's work as secretary to Norman Holmes Pearson, a professor of English and American Studies at Yale, as well as faculty advisor to the Yale Collection of American Literature and literary executor of both H. D. and Bryher. The papers span the years 1968-1985. The papers are housed in two boxes and are organized into four series: Correspondence, Writings of Others, Other Papers, and Photographs.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically in folders 1-30. The bulk of the correspondence is from Bryher and Norman Holmes Pearson. Wilda Hamerman's correspondence with Bryher largely concerns the completion of the manuscript for Bryher's The Days of Mars, which Hamerman typed, and includes some carbons of letters from Hamerman to Bryher. The bulk of Norman Holmes Pearson's correspondence to Wilda Hamerman dates from a 1970 trip that included Tahiti, New Caledonia, Australia, Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Taipei, and Japan. Other correspondence includes letters from Helene Brewer as she travelled in Japan in 1974, several thank you notes from Japanese students, and a copy of a letter from Kai Erikson, chair of the American Studies Program, to Norman Holmes Pearson's widow concerning an essay prize established in his name.
Series II, Writings of Others, is arranged alphabetically by author in folders 31-38. Writings include an uncorrected proof of Game of the Foxes by Ladislas Farago, several typescript and printed essays by Norman Holmes Pearson, a copy of a typescript outline for "How I Enjoyed Studying in America" by Tamotsu Nishiyama that mentions and thanks both Hamerman and Norman Holmes Pearson, and a typescript journal of a visit to London, probably kept by Pearson's daughter Elizabeth Tracy.
Series III, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically in folders 39-46. Other papers include an annual report form for the Department of English filled out by Norman Holmes Pearson, a program for an exhibit, "Two Estonian Artists," with an introduction by Pearson, clippings of obituaries of Pearson, a calendar from the State of Connecticut House of Representatives listing a resolution, "Expressing sympathy on the death of Professor Norman H. Pearson," an issue of Yale Library Associates Newsletter noting the presentation of a portrait of Pearson to the Beinecke Library, and a typescript emergency contact list, probably for a housesitter for the Pearsons during their 1970 trip.
Series IV, Photographs, is arranged chronologically in folders 47-52. Photographs include two snapshots of Norman Holmes Pearson, Susan Pearson, Wilda Hamerman, Martin Hamerman and others at a picnic, September 1970, and four photographs of Norman Holmes Pearson, including one of him holding two snakes and another showing him with Susan Pearson and an unidentified man.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Voyages and travels -- Asia; Voyages and travels -- Australia; Asia -- Description and travel; Australia -- Description and travel; Obituaries; Photographic prints; Authors; Bryher, 1894-1983 ( Days of mars); Farago, Ladislas ( Game of the foxes); Hamerman, Wilda; Nishiyama, Tamotsu, 1914-; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975; Yale University -- Employees; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1968-85; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. All letters are to Wilda Hamerman unless otherwise noted.
  - Brewer, Helene, 1974-76 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bryher, 1969-76 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
    Also includes carbons of letters from Wilda Hamerman to Bryher
  - Erikson, Kai, 1976 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Copy of letter to Mrs. Norman Holmes Pearson
  - Hashiguchi, Yasuo, 1970 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kamogawa, Takahiro, 1985 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kanaseki, Hisao, 1970 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kennelly, Peggy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11a)
  - Kerblat, Jeanne Blanchenay, 1983 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Leyda, Jay, 1977-84 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miyake, Takuo, 1970 Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nair, Eva W., 1975 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nishiyama, Tamotsu, 1970 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Noguchi, Kenji, 1985 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1968-75, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18-26)
  - Richardson, Helen K., 1971 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Copy of letter to Norman Holmes Pearson
  - Saito, ----, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Santos, Irene de Souse, 1974 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Unidentified, 1975, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Writings of Others, 1952-75; Series II; 8
  Series II, Writings of Others, is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Farago, Ladislas. Uncorrected proofs of Game of the Foxes, David McKay Co., ca. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Nishiyama, Tamotsu. "How I Enjoyed Studying in America," Copy of typescript book outline and excerpts (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Pearson, Norman Holmes
    - "Problems of Literary Executorship" Reprinted from Studies in Bibliography, Vol. 5, 1952-53 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "1970 Trip" Copy of typescript (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Includes trip itinerary
    - Address to the Hawthorne Society. Copy of typescript, signed, 1974 Dec 27 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "A Double Sense of Vision." In Yale Alumni Magazine. Vol. XXXIX, no. 3, 1975 Dec (Box 2, Folder 36)
      2 copies
    - "Melus" Copy of typescript, signed, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - [Tracy, Elizabeth]. "London -- 1972" Copy of typescript (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Other Papers, 1970-76; Series III; 6
  Series III, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Pearson, Norman Holmes. Department of English annual report form, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Norse Greenland. Copenhagen: The National Museum, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Yale Alumni Magazine. Vol. XXXV, no. 5, 1972 Feb (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Program, "Two Estonian Artists," with introduction by Norman Holmes Pearson, 1974 Nov 25 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Program for exhibition of works by Aleksis Rannit, poet, and Ediard Wiiralt, engraver
  - Clippings, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Includes obituaries and other newspaper articles relating to Norman Holmes Pearon.
  - State of Connecticut House of Representatives. Calendar, 1976 Feb 27 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    3 copies. Includes resolution, "Expressing sympathy on the death of Professor Norman H. Pearson"
  - Yale Library Associates Newsletter, 1976 Dec (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Notes presentation of portrait of Norman Holmes Pearson to the Beinecke Library
  - Emergency contact list, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Photographs, 1970-74; Series IV; 6
  Series IV, Photogaphs, is arranged chronologically
  - Martin Hamerman, Norman Holmes Pearson, and Susan Pearson. Color photograph, 1970 Sep (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Martin Hamerman, Norman Holmes Pearson, Wilda Hamerman, Hiroko Sato, and Rik Warch. Color photograph, 1970 Sep (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Norman Holmes Pearson. Portrait photograph, 1974 Jan (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Norman Holmes Pearson holding two snakes. Color photograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Norman Holmes Pearson. Color photograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Norman Holmes Pearson, Susan Pearson, and unidentified man (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Restricted Fragile, (1 broadside folder)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 43 (Box bsd, folder 53)